<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BIDS- Environmental</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on BIDS- Environmental</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 09:07:38 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2020 UC Reserve Fires</title>
      <link>/2022/07/01/2020-uc-reserve-fires/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 09:07:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/07/01/2020-uc-reserve-fires/</guid>
      <description>A short post overlaying a few different GIS layers on one another for a project we are working on. The databases used are large so I just show the code here with one final image instead of including them in the website repository. I needed to subset the fire perimeters from the Cal Fire database and overlap them with the UC Reserve perimeters. I also need to in-file some GPS coordinates of post fire sampling sites.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>California Pitcher Plant - Cobra Lily (Darlingtonia californica)</title>
      <link>/2022/06/15/california-pitcher-plant-cobra-lily-darlingtonia-californica/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/06/15/california-pitcher-plant-cobra-lily-darlingtonia-californica/</guid>
      <description>Spring is in full swing in the higher elevations around Mount Shasta and the surrounding ranges. I am always struck by the large patches of Cobra Lilies that grow along nutrient poor seeps in alpine meadows. I nearly always stop to take some photos and take in all the cool colors and shapes when out on training runs or hikes. I have made many observations of these over the past few years, but here is a quick post to pull out observations from GBIF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Edward Stuhl - Mount Shasta Wildflowers GBIF data</title>
      <link>/2022/06/01/edward-stuhl-mount-shasta-wildflowers-gbif-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/06/01/edward-stuhl-mount-shasta-wildflowers-gbif-data/</guid>
      <description>I have been working on identifying and painting various local wildflowers from the book Mount Shasta Wild Flowers A Field Guide featuring the water color paintings of Edward Stuhl. Stuhl was an artist and mountaineer that gradually painted 189 plants over a 50 year career exploring the greater Mount Shasta area. All of his paintings are available to view online at CSU Chico here. I was interested in what sort of publicly available observation data there was for some of the more rare species.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bay Area Insects</title>
      <link>/2022/05/15/bay-area-insects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/05/15/bay-area-insects/</guid>
      <description>Load the libraries.
library(rgbif) library(tidyverse) library(maps) I am working on a project using data collected at some of the UC Reserves. I needed to see what observations of insects were available in GBIF. I found this drawing tool for bounding boxes. Make sure to export it as OGC WKT and then you can create a POLYGON to use as your query area.
reserve_geometry &amp;lt;- paste(&amp;#39;POLYGON((-121.383275382 35.7567710044, -121.9875234289 36.3607073262, -122.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miracle Mile- Jeffrey&#39;s and Ponderosa Pine</title>
      <link>/2022/05/01/miracle-mile-jeffreys-and-ponderosa-pine/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/05/01/miracle-mile-jeffreys-and-ponderosa-pine/</guid>
      <description>I am continueing on my quest of checking off all the conifer species that occur in the Miracle Mile. I recently found some Jeffrey’s Pine (Pinus jeffreyi) on a trail run while on vacation in the San Bernadino mountains East of Los Angeles. This is in an area where there is also Ponderosa Pine (Pinus Ponderosa). Sometimes the species are confused with one another and can even form hybrids making identification difficult.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sugar Pine (Pinus lambertiana)</title>
      <link>/2022/04/15/sugar-pine-pinus-lambertiana/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/04/15/sugar-pine-pinus-lambertiana/</guid>
      <description>Another species found! I am attempting to ID all the conifer species that occur in the Miracle Mile while out on runs so I can make a visit to the Miracle Mile and ID all of them in one go.
These sugar pine cones are huge! I have a few in my pinecone collection that are greater than 35 cm! Sugar pines (Pinus lambertiana) are fairly common species and I see them on trail runs often.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mount Eddy Species</title>
      <link>/2022/04/01/mount-eddy-species/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/04/01/mount-eddy-species/</guid>
      <description>Pinus balfouriana
Western White Pine
Continuing to check off the conifer species that occur in the Miracle Mile so I can make a visit and try to ID all of them. Last summer I found some Foxtail Pine (Pinus balfouriana) and (Pinus monticola) near Mount Eddy in the Klammath Range (among others).
Load the libraries.
library(rgbif) library(tidyverse) library(data.table) library(maps) Load the data.
ski_data &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;../../../static/data/SkiTouring.csv&amp;quot;) setwd(&amp;quot;/Users/rjcmarkelz/Documents/Projects/THINK/git.repos/BIDS/DATA/&amp;quot;) TrailRun1 &amp;lt;- read.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miracle Mile Species 1- Pacific Yew (Taxus brevifolia)</title>
      <link>/2022/03/15/miracle-mile-species-1-pacific-yew-taxus-brevifolia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/03/15/miracle-mile-species-1-pacific-yew-taxus-brevifolia/</guid>
      <description>I have started checking off all the conifer species that occur in the Miracle Mile. I recently found some Pacific Yew (Taxus brevifolia) on a trail run with a friend. This was also my first post to iNaturalist. A good time to take a look at the data.
Load the libraries.
library(rinat) library(tidyverse) Load the data.
TrailRun1 &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;../../../static/data/TrailRun_PacYew.csv&amp;quot;) glimpse(TrailRun1) ## Rows: 7,077 ## Columns: 10 ## $ X &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, … ## $ timestamp &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt; &amp;quot;2022-02-27 16:41:35&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;2022-02-27 16:41:43&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;2022-02-… ## $ position_lat &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA,… ## $ position_long &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA,… ## $ distance &amp;lt;int&amp;gt; 0, 21, 24, 28, 32, 36, 41, 41, 51, 55, 59, 64, 68, 72, … ## $ altitude &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; NA, 791.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trout and Food Species</title>
      <link>/2022/03/01/trout-and-food-species/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/03/01/trout-and-food-species/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post we will look at some spatial data of Rainbow Trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) and one of thier food sources Blue Winged Olives (Baetis tricaudatus). We will take a look using publically available observation data from the GBIF database. See previous posts here and here for other examples of species occurance data.
Load the necessary R libraries.
library(rgbif) library(tidyverse) library(data.table) library(maps) library(leaflet) Pull in the species observation data from GBIF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ski Touring Movement Data</title>
      <link>/2022/02/15/ski-touring-movement-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/02/15/ski-touring-movement-data/</guid>
      <description>When thinking about how to combine datasets to ask more complex questions it is important to determine where the overlaps in the datasets might be. As an example, The Mount Shasta Avalanche Center keeps records of seasonal weather and avalanche forecast data that I discussed in a previous post. I just made a small movement dataset from some of the ski tours I have done in the Mount Shasta area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UC Reserve System Environmental Data - 1</title>
      <link>/2022/02/01/uc-reserve-system-environmental-data-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/02/01/uc-reserve-system-environmental-data-1/</guid>
      <description>This post was to fulfill two small goals. I wanted to explore the publicly available UC Reserve Data and learn how to host small datasets within the blogdown blog framework that this website is written in. I also wanted to make sure I could save small output analyses and come back to them at a later date.
There is a good discussion of how hugo can handle internal datasets and how to organize the datasets here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scraping Weather Data</title>
      <link>/2022/01/15/scraping-weather-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/01/15/scraping-weather-data/</guid>
      <description>A quick post showing how to extract data from a website and make a few plots. I chose the Mount Shasta Avalanche Center data because I monitor this everyday throughout the season to see how the avalanche forecast changes and how the snowpack is developing.
R vest There is a great website scraping package that is part of the tidyverse called Rvest. Check out the Documentation.
library(rvest) library(tidyverse) library(lubridate) html &amp;lt;- read_html(&amp;quot;https://www.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zotero &#43; Obsidian</title>
      <link>/2022/01/01/zotero-obsidian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/01/01/zotero-obsidian/</guid>
      <description>Bibliography Software + Obsidian Keeping track of scientific papers, code tutorials and snippets, as well as highlighting from digital books has gotten a lot easier of over the past few years. Check out Zotero here. If you are completely new to Zotero work through this quickstart tutorial by Kartcher and Zelle. I have been using Zotero almost exclusively for the past 11 years for PDF management because it has plugins for Word or Google documents to quickly create linked bibliographies for research papers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Obsidian</title>
      <link>/2021/12/15/introduction-to-obsidian/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/12/15/introduction-to-obsidian/</guid>
      <description>What is it? Obsidian is a way to take notes in markdown and link those notes together. Linking ideas is a powerful way to form new ones and reinforce old ones. Obsidian is fairly flexible, has a large number of extensions, an active community for ideas and troubleshooting, and is kind of an addictive productivity tool.
Why is it interesting? I was originally attracted to this option because I spend a lot of my time making markdown documents as part of daily research activities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Links</title>
      <link>/page/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/page/links/</guid>
      <description>General Datasets USFS Fire Rasters
UC Reserve Data
ACE California Wildlife DB
Terrestrial Significant Habitats
Terrestrial Connectivity Model
Terrestrial Resilience Maps
pyregence fire 17TB
cal conservation genomics
Geospatial Innovation Facility
Geospatial Biodiversity Database
Specific GBIF datasets
Weislander Historic Data
Cal Flora
UC Reserve System Data Portal
UC Collections
NOAA Climate, Weather, Tides
NOAA Climate Data Online
Species List
Merced Data
trefle dataset
inaturalist
cal wildlife
cal wildlife database
forest service global change</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MLK Shoreline iNaturalist data</title>
      <link>/2021/06/23/inaturalist-mlk-nature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/06/23/inaturalist-mlk-nature/</guid>
      <description>MLK Shoreline and iNaturalist Observations For the last few years I commuted to work most days by bicycle along the Martin Luther King Jr. Regional Shoreline Park in Oakland, CA. This will be a series of data science posts exploring personal data collected by my smart watch and publicly available weather, nature and biodiversity data collected in this park. It is my hope that this will show into the brain of how a data scientist thinks, learns, asks questions, creates models, and visualizes data from right in their back yard through a series of posts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miracle Mile Conifer Species</title>
      <link>/2021/06/17/gbif-miracle-mile-species/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/06/17/gbif-miracle-mile-species/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Overall, my research aims to understand how environmental factors, like wild fires, influence biodiversity. One of the most used databases for measuring biodiversity is the Global Biodiversity Information Facility GBIF. This is post is a brief introduction of how to use GBIF, using the example of mapping a few conifer species in California.
Load the libraries library(rgbif) library(tidyverse) library(data.table) library(maps) library(leaflet)   Part 1 -Mapping one species Using the R package function occ_data() request data from the GBIF database with the species name, selecting the observations that have a coordinate, and limiting the query to 10000 observations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biodiversity and Fire</title>
      <link>/project/biodiversity-fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/biodiversity-fire/</guid>
      <description>About project A project that combines data science, modeling, biodiversity, invasive species and fire to answer questions across Californian ecosystems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2014 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/page/about/</guid>
      <description>About Work As we enter an era of unprecedented amounts of data, we face the defining challenge of our age - global environmental change. From automated environmental sensors to satellite imaging to emerging DNA technologies, the data that describes the world around us will aid in how we approach the many challenges of climate change. By harnessing this data we can observe how are planet is changing and through data science approaches allow us to predict, and further define, how we as a society can respond and remediate the effects of our climate uncertain future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact Page</title>
      <link>/page/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2014 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/page/contact/</guid>
      <description>Contact Email: rjcmarkelz {at} berkeley.edu Twitter: rjcmarkelz Github: rjcmarkelz linkedin: codymarkelz </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
