<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on BIDS- Environmental</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on BIDS- Environmental</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 09:07:38 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Trout and Food Species</title>
      <link>/2022/03/01/trout-and-food-species/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/03/01/trout-and-food-species/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this post we will look at some spatial data of Rainbow Trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) and one of thier food sources Blue Winged Olives (Baetis tricaudatus). We will take a look using publically available observation data from the GBIF database. See previous posts here and here for other examples of species occurance data.
Load the necessary R libraries.
library(rgbif) library(tidyverse) library(data.table) library(maps) library(leaflet) Pull in the species observation data from GBIF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ski Touring Movement Data</title>
      <link>/2022/02/15/ski-touring-movement-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/02/15/ski-touring-movement-data/</guid>
      <description>When thinking about how to combine datasets to ask more complex questions it is important to determine where the overlaps in the datasets might be. As an example, The Mount Shasta Avalanche Center keeps records of seasonal weather and avalanche forecast data that I discussed in a previous post. I just made a small movement dataset from some of the ski tours I have done in the Mount Shasta area.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UC Reserve System Environmental Data - 1</title>
      <link>/2022/02/01/uc-reserve-system-environmental-data-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/02/01/uc-reserve-system-environmental-data-1/</guid>
      <description>This post was to fulfill two small goals. I wanted to explore the publicly available UC Reserve Data and learn how to host small datasets within the blogdown blog framework that this website is written in. I also wanted to make sure I could save small output analyses and come back to them at a later date.
There is a good discussion of how hugo can handle internal datasets and how to organize the datasets here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scraping Weather Data</title>
      <link>/2022/01/15/scraping-weather-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/01/15/scraping-weather-data/</guid>
      <description>A quick post showing how to extract data from a website and make a few plots. I chose the Mount Shasta Avalanche Center data because I monitor this everyday throughout the season to see how the avalanche forecast changes and how the snowpack is developing.
R vest There is a great website scraping package that is part of the tidyverse called Rvest. Check out the Documentation.
library(rvest) library(tidyverse) library(lubridate) html &amp;lt;- read_html(&amp;quot;https://www.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zotero &#43; Obsidian</title>
      <link>/2022/01/01/zotero-obsidian/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2022/01/01/zotero-obsidian/</guid>
      <description>Bibliography Software + Obsidian Keeping track of scientific papers, code tutorials and snippets, as well as highlighting from digital books has gotten a lot easier of over the past few years. Check out Zotero here. If you are completely new to Zotero work through this quickstart tutorial by Kartcher and Zelle. I have been using Zotero almost exclusively for the past 11 years for PDF management because it has plugins for Word or Google documents to quickly create linked bibliographies for research papers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Obsidian</title>
      <link>/2021/12/15/introduction-to-obsidian/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 09:07:38 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/12/15/introduction-to-obsidian/</guid>
      <description>What is it? Obsidian is a way to take notes in markdown and link those notes together. Linking ideas is a powerful way to form new ones and reinforce old ones. Obsidian is fairly flexible, has a large number of extensions, an active community for ideas and troubleshooting, and is kind of an addictive productivity tool.
Why is it interesting? I was originally attracted to this option because I spend a lot of my time making markdown documents as part of daily research activities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MLK Shoreline iNaturalist data</title>
      <link>/2021/06/23/inaturalist-mlk-nature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/06/23/inaturalist-mlk-nature/</guid>
      <description>MLK Shoreline and iNaturalist Observations For the last few years I commuted to work most days by bicycle along the Martin Luther King Jr. Regional Shoreline Park in Oakland, CA. This will be a series of data science posts exploring personal data collected by my smart watch and publicly available weather, nature and biodiversity data collected in this park. It is my hope that this will show into the brain of how a data scientist thinks, learns, asks questions, creates models, and visualizes data from right in their back yard through a series of posts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miracle Mile Conifer Species</title>
      <link>/2021/06/17/gbif-miracle-mile-species/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/06/17/gbif-miracle-mile-species/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Overall, my research aims to understand how environmental factors, like wild fires, influence biodiversity. One of the most used databases for measuring biodiversity is the Global Biodiversity Information Facility GBIF. This is post is a brief introduction of how to use GBIF, using the example of mapping a few conifer species in California.
Load the libraries library(rgbif) library(tidyverse) library(data.table) library(maps) library(leaflet)   Part 1 -Mapping one species Using the R package function occ_data() request data from the GBIF database with the species name, selecting the observations that have a coordinate, and limiting the query to 10000 observations.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
